Finding Aid for Robert Twining collection
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert Twining collection 1925-1966 1930-1957
Twining, Robert
2013154 Aa2 UA1
The Robert Twining collection is comprised of photographs, scrapbooks, slides, negatives, and films of Camp Al-Gon-Quian. Located on Burt Lake, Michigan, the camp was founded in 1925 by Herbert H. Twining as a summer camp for boys. The materials in the collection detail activities of Camp Al-Gon-Quian, such as fishing, archery, and horseback riding. There are also materials relating to Camp Mississauga, which was a camp for older boys in Canada.
12 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Robert Twining (Donor No. 10700 ) in December, 2011
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The site that is now Camp Al-Gon-Quian was originally a farm on Burt Lake in Northern Michigan, just east of Petoskey. In 1925, Herbert H. Twining purchased the land with the intent to start a summer camp. Twining was a University of Michigan graduate (1923), who initially wanted to be a medical doctor. However, an eye injury as a child prevented this and instead Twining pursued a profession that he found to be similar: establishing a private boys' camp on the leading edge of camp programming.
Twining chose the name Al-Gon-Quian because he believed that was a possible Native American expression for "bow of a canoe." Twining also borrowed several Native American names for the camper groups. He divided the campers into groups by age, grade, height and weight. Throughout the years, the tribes within the camp included the Ottawa, Chippewa, Cree, Ojibwa, Miami, Nipissing and Mississauga. One common element that joined these native tribes together is that they were a part of the Algonquian linguistic family and spoke Algonquian when together.
In 1925, Twining opened camp for its first season. Sessions lasted 8 weeks, and boys came from all over Michigan and surrounding states. It was a popular summertime activity for prominent families from the Ann Arbor community and the Midwest. Well known attendees include: the Proctor & Gamble sons of Cincinnati, the Wrigleys of Chicago, the Strohs of Detroit and Grosse Pointe, and the children of University of Michigan figures Alvin Bentley, C.S. Mott and G. Mennen Williams. Prominent members of the university community that served as staff members include Bennie Oosterbaan, Dr. Roger Howell, Roscoe Bonisteel, E. Blythe Stason and James B. Edmonson.
In addition to providing a fun outdoor experience for campers, Camp Al-Gon-Quian aimed to improve the character of young men. In 1932, the aims of camp were to develop strength of character, a purpose in life, a clear moral character, self-reliance and the ability to achieve. This was accomplished through two months of camaraderie and living in the outdoors away from the stresses of city life.
Twining was well-recognized in the camping community and actively involved with the American Camp Association, of which he was the first national president in 1935. He was the director of Al-Gon-Quian for 42 years until his retirement in 1967, when he sold the camp to the Ann Arbor YMCA.
Source: Ann Arbor YMCA Website http://www.annarborymca.org/programs/camp-al-gon-quian/history.php
The collection contains two series: Photographs and Film.
Subjects:
Al-Gon-Quian Boys Camp (Burt Lake, Mich.); Archery--Michigan.; Backpacking--Michigan.; Camping--Michigan.; Camps--Michigan.; Canoes--Michigan.; Handicraft--Michigan.; Hiking--Michigan.; Horseback riding--Michigan.; Sailing--Michigan.; Shooting--Michigan.; Swimming--Michigan.; Travel--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Black-and-white negatives.; Black-and-white slides.; Color slides.; Home movies.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Photographs
  Photographs (5 linear feet) are organized by subject. Almost all of the photographs and slides in the series are black and white. Most of the photographs are group photos, which are formal and informal group shots of the campers. Staff group photos can be found in the "staff" folder. A bulk of the series consists of water sports (swimming, sailing, canoeing), horseback riding, sports (rifle shooting, archery, tennis), other activities (educational and social), and daily activities (eating in dining hall, visiting nurse, getting haircuts). Most of the photographs are undated. In Box 4, there is a folder entitled, "photos in envelopes," which are photos of various activities that were labeled in envelopes. A small number of the photos do not seem to be related to the camp, but may be photos of Robert Twining's family. These photos are found in the unidentified folder.
  In addition to seven scrapbooks with photos about camp life and travels in Ontario, Canada, Box 5 includes one folder with a brochure advertising the camp and one folder that contains loose notes. Four of the scrapbooks have labels with information such as names, date, and location. This box also contains the alphabetical and chronological lists of campers and counselors prepared in 2012 Camp Al-Gon-Quian Camper and Counselor files, 1925-1967.
  The series also contains slides (4.5 linear feet). Box 6 contains loose slides that were stored in labeled envelopes. There are also loose slides that include an index to slide contents. The rest of the slides are ordered by the same subjects that the photographs are sorted by. There are a large amount of undated slides, but many contain descriptions. Box 8 contains slides that are in boxes with descriptive information. There is one box of 35 mm glass slides that should be handled with caution.
  Finally, the series contains a box of photo negatives (.5 linear feet). These negatives have been arranged by subject to mirror the same organization as the photographs. Some of the negatives include their corresponding photograph.
  - Animals, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Camp Hayo-Went-Ha circa 1922 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Camp Mississauga, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Crafts, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Daily activities, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Entertainment, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Flag-raising ceremonies, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Group photos, 32 folders (Box 1)
  - Group photos, 30 folders (Box 2)
  - Group photos, 25 photos (Folder 1)
  - Hiking and camping, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Horseback riding, 31 folders (Box 2)
  - Hunting and fishing, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Individuals, 11 folders (Box 3)
  - In envelopes, 4 folders (Box 3)
    (various subjects)
  - Landscapes, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Other activities, 15 folders (Box 3)
  - Other activities, 5 photos (Folder 1)
  - Property, 11 folders (Box 3)
  - Sports, 33 folders (Box 3)
  - Staff, 14 folders (Box 4)
  - Travel, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Unidentified, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Water sports, 31 folders (Box 4)
  - Crafts, 1 photo (Box 12)
  - Daily activities, 20 photos (Box 12)
  - Flag-raising ceremony, 1 photo (Box 12)
  - Group photos, 5 photos (Box 12)
  - Horseback riding, 24 photos (Box 12)
  - Other activities, 1 photo (Box 12)
  - Property, 1 photo (Box 12)
  - Water sports, 25 photos (Box 12)
  - Water sports, 8 photos (Folder 1)
  - Brochure (Box 5)
  - Camp Al-Gon-Quian Camper and Counselor files, 1925-1967, 2012 (Box 5)
  - Loose Notes, 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook, labeled 1929 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, labeled 1930 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, labeled 1935 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook 1954 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, labeled undated (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, Property of Camp Al-Gon-Quian undated (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook undated (Box 5)
  - Slides
    - Slides in envelopes
      - Archery, 2 slides (Box 6)
      - Canoeing, 2 slides (Box 6)
      - Church under the trees and at the shrine, 1 slide (Box 6)
      - Crafts, 2 slides (Box 6)
      - Good food, plenty of rest, a place to go if you don't feel well, 3 slides (Box 6)
      - Nature and camp craft, 4 slides (Box 6)
      - Riding, 10 slides (Box 6)
      - Riflery, 2 slides (Box 6)
      - Sailing, 1 slide (Box 6)
      - Slides with slide index, 112 slides (Box 6)
      - Tennis, 3 slides (Box 6)
      - The camp awakes, 2 slides (Box 6)
      - Waterfront and swimming, 8 slides (Box 6)
    - Sorted Slides
      - Crafts, 25 slides (Box 6)
      - Daily Activities, 75 slides (Box 6)
      - Entertainment, 15 slides (Box 6)
      - Flag-raising ceremonies, 30 slides (Box 6)
      - Group photos, 150 slides (Box 6)
      - Hiking and camping, 25 slides (Box 6)
      - Horseback riding, 270 slides (Box 6)
      - Hunting and fishing, 6 slides (Box 6)
      - Individuals, 20 slides (Box 6)
      - Landscapes, 25 slides (Box 6)
      - Other activities, 175 slides (Box 6)
      - Property, 90 slides (Box 6)
      - Sports, 200 slides (Box 6)
      - Staff, 30 slides (Box 6)
      - Travel, 340 slides (Box 6)
      - Water Sports, 375 slides (Box 7)
    - Boxed slides
      - All camp shots, cabin groups, archery, rifle 1959 40 slides (Box 8)
      - Cabin formal and informal, camp group pictures, 35 slides (Box 8)
      - Canoe trips, launching the team, campers arrive 1959 30 slides (Box 8)
      - Camp Al-Gon-Quian pictures and slides (Box 8)
        (glass slides)
      - Charlevoix meet, tennis, archery, track meet 1958 25 slides (Box 8)
      - Evening program, fishing, canoeing, 30 slides (Box 8)
      - General camp, 15 slides (Box 8)
      - Good but not best, 40 slides (Box 8)
      - Good shots but not best, 40 slides (Box 8)
      - Good but not best, 13 slides (Box 8)
      - Horses, rodeo, tennis, track meet 1959 40 slides (Box 8)
      - Horse show and final day 1959 34 slides (Box 8)
      - Klondike Day, waterfront scenes, canoeing and boat contests, sailing, swim meet, water skiing, riding, 40 slides (Box 8)
      - Last week of camp, lake swim, horseshow, counselor's snow, camp craft contest, 40 slides (Box 8)
      - Meets, athletics, swimming, water skiing 1959 43 slides (Box 8)
      - Nip truck trip 1959 35 slides (Box 8)
  - Photo Negatives
    - 1941 Negatives, approximately 30 negatives (Box 9)
    - 1957 Negatives, approximately 90 negatives (Box 9)
    - Animals, 4 negatives (Box 9)
    - Camp Mississauga, 4 negatives (Box 9)
    - Camp Negatives, approximately 25 negatives (Box 9)
    - Flag-raising ceremony, 1 negative (Box 9)
    - Group photos, 11 negatives, 2 photos (Box 9)
    - Hiking and camping, 19 negatives, 2 photos (Box 9)
    - Hunting and fishing, 4 negatives (Box 9)
    - Individuals, 2 negatives (Box 9)
    - Landscapes, 11 negatives, 1 photo (Box 9)
    - Sports, 1 negative (Box 9)
    - Travel, 36 negatives, 3 photos (Box 9)
    - Unidentified, 3 negatives (Box 9)
    - Water sports, 2 negatives (Box 9)
- Film
  The Film series (2 linear feet) contains 20 reels of 16 mm film recording activities of Camp Al-Gon-Quian. Some of the films are described on the box, but many contain no description. They date from 1930-1951.
  - Camp Mississauga, Drowning Ridge, towing canoes, fishing in Lake Superior 1930 (Box 10)
  - Hudson Bay Trip 1931-1932 (Box 10)
  - Old Lane Hall, black and white 1932-1934 (Box 10)
  - Al-Gon-Quian 1932 (Box 10)
  - Canadian Camp 1932 (Box 10)
  - Horseshow and Boxing 1932 (Box 10)
  - First Part of Hudson Bay Trip,1933 (Box 10)
  - Petoskey Winter Sports; 1933 (Box 10)
  - East Coast Hudson Bay trip 1934 (Box 10)
  - Camp Al-Gon-Quian 1935 (Box 10)
  - 1936 (Box 10)
  - 1942 (Box 10)
  - 1948 (Box 10)
  - Movie Shorts 1948 (Box 10)
  - 1948 (Box 10)
  - 1949 (Box 10)
  - Sailing, rifle range close up, sailing races, chip cruise 1950 (Box 10)
  - Honeymoon-short, [foot?] ball 1932, 1951 (Box 10)
  - Horse show, course paddling, second cuts 1951 (Box 10)
  - Best cuts 1951 (Box 10)
  - Track, swim, riding trip, first cuts 1951 (Box 10)
  - Al-Gon-Quian undated (Box 10)
  - Archery, tennis courts, and view of fields undated (Box 10)
  - Boat undated (Box 10)
  - Broke undated (Box 10)
  - Camp undated (Box 10)
  - Camp Al-Gon-Quian undated (Box 10)
  - Old Al-Gon-Quian past undated (Box 10)
  - No description, undated, 10 reels (Box 10)
  - Camp 1946 (Box 11)
  - 1949 (Box 11)
  - Camp Al-Gon-Quian, by RET 1950 (Box 11)
  - 1952 trip, camp 1955 (Box 11)
  - Camp Al-Gon-Quian 1955 (Box 11)
  - Al-Gon-Quian undated (Box 11)
  - No description, undated, 2 reels (Box 11)